<res>
	<cover vnum="01" inum="01">The world beyond our Milky Way galaxy contains several exciting objects. Shown here are two galaxies IC 2200 - IC 2200 A which form a binary system in gravitational interaction. <i>(Observed at the Los Campanas Observatory, Chile on 29 January 1995; processed of IUCAA.)</i></cover>
	<cover vnum="01" inum="02">Photographs of the total solar eclipse which was visible in northern India on 24 October 1995.</cover>
	<cover vnum="01" inum="03">A space-filling model of a self-assembly of five ligands of two different types and six Cu( I ) ions spontaneously producing a cage structure. See the article by J. -M. Lehn for details.</cover>
	<cover vnum="01" inum="04">In Africa, a blackthroated honeyguide leads a honeybadger to a wild beehive, in one of the most striking examples of the evolution of mutualistic relationships in the living world. (illustration by Sanjeev Nayak)</cover>
	<cover vnum="01" inum="05">The fern on the cover is a computer generated fractal. It was programmed by C E Prakash of the Supercomputer Education and Research Centre, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore, on a Silicon Graphics workstation. The method of generation is described by M F Barnsley in his book 'Fractals Everywhere' (Academic Press, New York, 1988).</cover>
	<cover vnum="01" inum="06">Comet C/1996 B2 (Hyakutake) on 23 March 1996 from Vainu Bappu Observatory, Kavalur, Indian Institute of Astrophysics (Photographed by K Kuppuswamy and Pavan Chakraborty; Courtesy : Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bangalore 560 034.)</cover>
	<cover vnum="01" inum="07">A herd of Sambar quench their thirst at a water hole early in the morning in Sariska Tiger Reserve, Rajasthan. On the right are two males, one in hard antler and one that has just shed its antlers. Females and a large fawn are also visible (Photograph by T R Shankar Raman).</cover>
	<cover vnum="01" inum="08">Melting of snow: Birth of Himalayan river in Kumaun (at Milam glacier).</cover>
	<cover vnum="01" inum="09">The cover illustration is from Johannes Kepler's book. He believed that the relative distances of planets from the sun could be understood based on a model involving the five regular solids. Unlike his laws of planetary motion, this idea of Kelpler's has not survived to the present day.</cover>
	<cover vnum="01" inum="10">Maize cobs displaying variegated Kernel phenotype. Variations are due to transposable elements. Photographs kindly provided by B M Prasanna of Indian Agricultural Research Institute, New Delhi.</cover>
	<cover vnum="01" inum="11">An INSATID cloud picture of the October 1996 Arabian Sea Cyclone taken at 0600 GMT on October 23, 1996. It covers the region between 10° Sand 45° N and 44° E and 105°E. Another weaker vortex is noted around Andaman-Nicobar islands. These vortices are embedded on the large scale Inter Tropical Convergence Zone (ITCZ) from Indonesia to Arabian Sea. (Courtesy India Meteorological Department)</cover>
	<cover vnum="01" inum="12">SRL Levitates Woman 5cm with Single Crystal YBCO. Researchers at the International Superconductivity Technology Center's Superconductivity Research Laboratory (SRL) reported that they have levitated a woman (Ms Asakawa) with 5 centimeters clearance using (HTS) materials, beating the old record (5 millimeters) a factor of ten.</cover>
	<cover vnum="02" inum="01">The cover picture shows two representations of a nanotube made of 630 carbon atoms. The structure British jail can still be seen a small distance away. The first plantations here employed Chinese prisoners of war (from the opium wars) as labourers. (Kartik Shanker)</cover>
	<cover vnum="02" inum="02">Carrington tea estate, in the Upper Nilgiris, was established in the mid 1800s. The remains of an old British jail can still be seen a small distance away. The first plantations here employed Chinese prisoners of war (from the opium wars) as labourers. (Kartik Shanker)</cover>
	<cover vnum="02" inum="03">A calico cat. The mosaic pattern of coat colour in this female cat is related to X-chromosome inactivation. (Courtesy A J F Griffiths)</cover>
	<cover vnum="02" inum="04">This figure is from a famous book <i>Birth and death of the Sun</i> by the physicist George Gamow. He was an artist as well and prepared his own illustrations! He explains the diagram as follows: The relationship between the radii and the masses of cold stellar bodies, according to the calculations of the Indian astrophysicists Chandrasekhar and Kothari. The symbols ☾, ⊕, ♭, and ♃, respectively represent the moon, the earth, Saturn, and Jupiter. Note that for masses greater than 460,000 times the mass of the earth the radius becomes zero! The words for mass and radius are in Dr. Chandrasekhar's original Tamil.</cover>
	<cover vnum="02" inum="05">The cover photograph shows a remarkable dye which has different colours in different solvents. The structure of the molecule is shown on top and the formulae of the solvents are indicated above each solution. For a detailed account on this Molecular Chameleon, see the Feature Article on page 69.</cover>
	<cover vnum="02" inum="06">The cover photograph shows a familiar toy, which apparently executes perpetual motion. The principles of thermodynamics determining the action of the `Thirsty Bird' are discussed in the classroom section.</cover>
	<cover vnum="02" inum="07">Colour Schlieren photograph of the flow past the first stage of a typical launch vehicle model at a Mach number of 2.5 and Angle of Attack of 40° taken in the 1.2m trisonic wind tunnel at NAL. Shock-wave and expansion waves around the model can be clearly seen. (Courtesy: Wind Tunnel Laboratory, NAL, Bangalore)</cover>
	<cover vnum="02" inum="08">Painting with perspective (see the article by S Ramanan on Projective Geometry)</cover>
	<cover vnum="02" inum="09">A photograph of a small sail boat obtained using the principle of polarization of light. (Also see article by Vilas Gohad.)</cover>
	<cover vnum="02" inum="10">A portion of the presidential panorama showing the Sojourner Rover taking its APXS measurement of Yogi. (Courtesy NASA)</cover>
	<cover vnum="02" inum="11">Californian specimen of the <i>Haliotidae</i>, known locally as the abalone. Such shells are found in the waters around California and are most remarkable for displaying a vivid colouration of the mother-of-pearl lining of the shell. (Ref: Iridescent Shells - C V Raman. <i>Proc. Indian Acad. Sci.</i> A1. 567-573, 1934.)</cover>
	<cover vnum="02" inum="12">The cover photograph (colour enhanced to show the contrast) shows a dark blue solution of solvated electrons generated by adding a little sodium metal to liquid ammonia at -33° C.</cover>
	<cover vnum="03" inum="01">Stages of man's long march from apelike ancestors to Homo sapiens. (Also see Research News)</cover>
	<cover vnum="03" inum="02">An artist's impression of an 'atomic fountain', one of the devices made possible by the work of this year's physics Nobel Prize winners. The atoms are cooled by laser beams (see article pp.16-27 in this issue) which can also be used to give them a controlled vertical velocity. They traverse the radio frequency cavity (dark box) twice. There is resonance between the micro-waves in the cavity and the atoms, and the electrical oscillations act as the atomic clock.</cover>
	<cover vnum="03" inum="03">Ribbon structure of thymidylate synthase that has been engineered to function at high temperatures. (Also see the article on page 32).</cover>
	<cover vnum="03" inum="04">Views of <i>saturn's rings</i> from the Voyager spacecraft. Top left - the planet and its rings; top right - a closer view: note satellites in the background, gap in the rings, and shadows; bottom left &#38; right - fine structure in the rings caused by satellite perturbations (chaos and resonance play an important role, see pages 6-14 and 43-53). (Courtesy NASA)</cover>
	<cover vnum="03" inum="05">The Nilgiri tahr (<i>Hemigragus hylocritus</i>) is a relative of the wild goats. Fewer than 2000 of them survive in the montane grasslands of the Western Ghats in Tamil Nadu and Kerala.</cover>
	<cover vnum="03" inum="06">The structure of Insulin dimer solved by Dorothy Hodgkin and coworkers. This representation clearly shows the dimer interface. The α-helices and the β-sheets (arrow) are shown in gold and transparent green, respectively.</cover>
	<cover vnum="03" inum="07">An abstract painting by Homi J Bhabha</cover>
	<cover vnum="03" inum="08">A female wreathed hornbill (<i>Rhyticeros undulatus</i>), a species found in north-east India and south-east Asia, has a corrugated casque. The bare skin of the throat pouch and the area around the eye add a dash of colour to its appearance. (Photo Credit: M D Madhusudan)</cover>
	<cover vnum="03" inum="09">Listening to the heavens: a view of the Giant Metrewave Radio Telescope near Pune.</cover>
	<cover vnum="03" inum="10">Corona due to spherical particles of nearly the same size.</cover>
	<cover vnum="03" inum="11">This is a picture of Cray 2 supercomputer designed by Seymour Cray.</cover>
	<cover vnum="03" inum="12">The cover picture provides a schematic summary of the major themes covered in the six part series of articles on ``Molecules to Materials". The top left corner shows an organic metal. The structure of fullerene (C<sub>60</sub>) is shown on the top right. It is a component of an organic ferromagnetic material. The molecule in the bottom left has high second-harmonic generation (SHG) efficiency. The polymer in the bottom right is an electroluminescent material.</cover>
	<cover vnum="04" inum="01">Regular Solids (See the article `Crossing Bridges')</cover>
	<cover vnum="04" inum="02">Chemical properties of molecules are aften interpreted in terms of the shapes and energies of the wave functions corresponding to their highest occupied molecular orbital (HOMO) and the lowest unoccupied molecular orbital (LUMO). The cover picture shows schematic representations of the LUMOs of the fullerene C<sub>60</sub> and benzene. Note that the LUMO of C<sub>60</sub> has t<sub>1u</sub> symmetry (triply degenerate) while the LUMO of benzene has e<sub>2u</sub> symmetry (doubly degenerate). Only one orbital for each molecule is shown.</cover>
	<cover vnum="04" inum="03">Rice, coconut and backwaters: A typical landscape of Kuttanad. (See article on p.62) Photocredit: P Pramod</cover>
	<cover vnum="04" inum="04">Infrastructure of the new neutrino experiment at a nuclear power station near the village of Chooz. (Reproduced with permission from CERN Courier)</cover>
	<cover vnum="04" inum="05">The harpsichord is a keyboard instrument with sound produced by the mechanism, plucking the strings. It dates from the early 16th century. (Courtesy: New York Public Library)</cover>
	<cover vnum="04" inum="06"><i>Barapasaurus tagorei</i>, the Dinosaur at ISI, Calcutta (Courtesy: ISI, Calcutta) For more details, see p. 100.</cover>
	<cover vnum="04" inum="07">A mating pair of olive ridleys. (Kartik Shanker)</cover>
	<cover vnum="04" inum="08">A sketch depicting the process of eighteenth century surveying, by Henry Beighton (1728) (Reproduced from <i>The Mapmakers - The Story of the Great Pioneers in Cartography from Antiquity to the Space Age)</i></cover>
	<cover vnum="04" inum="09">A few eye mutants of <i>Drosophila melanogaster.</i> (See the Classroom section for more details)</cover>
	<cover vnum="04" inum="10">Cyclic symmetry in echinids (Class Ophiodea, Phylum Echinodermata). Reproduced from from Weyl's <i>Symmetry</i>. Princeton University Press.</cover>
	<cover vnum="04" inum="11">Electron micrograph of phage T4 (right) and mycobacteriophage l3 (left). Max Delbrück contributed to our understanding of the genetics of phage T4. Phage l3 was isolated and its biology has been investigated at IISc by T Ramakrishnan and his colleagues. (Courtesy V Nagaraja)</cover>
	<cover vnum="04" inum="12">A study of electrostatic potential can provide useful guidelines for investigating weak molecular clusters. A variety of models incorporating electrostatics as a principle ingredient have been developed for probing such complexes. The cover page shows a cluster of six water molecules networked by OH...O hydrogen bond. Isosurfaces of MESP values `X=-105' and `Y=1050' kJ mol<sup>-1</sup> are superposed on the corresponding ball and stick model in order to bring out the complementary lock-and-key arrangement.</cover>
	<cover vnum="05" inum="01">Edison's Phonograph (Courtesy: Sujit K Sikdar</cover>
	<cover vnum="05" inum="02">The caterpillar of the European moth <i>Biston betularia</i> which mimics a twig, in color, shape and the position in which it rests.</cover>
	<cover vnum="05" inum="03">Silver-lining among bushes and hedges. (Picture of common Silverline Butterfly) Photo: Kunhikrishnan</cover>
	<cover vnum="05" inum="04">Black holes are an important consequence of Einstein's theory of gravitation. Astronomers believe that some strong sources of X-rays consist of a normal star and a black hole orbiting around each other. Note that the black hole, on the right, is itself invisible but surrounded by a swirling disc of hot gas which falls into it from the companion star.</cover>
	<cover vnum="05" inum="05">1. Schematic diagram of a eukaryotic cell showing various intracellular organelles in which proteins are trafficked and the route of protein secretion outside (arrows). 2. Representation of the signal hypothesis. Proteins trafficking to different organelles are shown in brown and the signal sequences are indicated in red. 3. A model showing early events in the entry of secretory proteins in the endoplasmic reticulum. The protein-conducting channel discovered by Blobel is labeled as membrane channel.</cover>
	<cover vnum="05" inum="06">INSAT - 2E CCD Image Acquired on 16 April 1999. (Photo courtesy: Dr S Rangarajan, ISRO, Bangalore).</cover>
	<cover vnum="05" inum="07">Auroral Bands (Photo courtesy: Prof. Chanchal Uberoi, IISc, Bangalore).</cover>
	<cover vnum="05" inum="08">Star Birth in the Trifid Nebula: This NASA Hubble Space Telescope image of the Trifid Nebula reveals a stellar nursery being torn apart by radiation from a nearby, massive star. The picture also provides a peek at embryonic stars that are forming within an ill-fated cloud of dust and gas, which is destined to be eaten away by the glare from the massive neighbor. This stellar activity is a beautiful example of how the life cycle of stars like our Sun is intimately connected with their more powerful siblings. Courtesy: NASA and Jeff Hester (Arizona State University).</cover>
	<cover vnum="05" inum="09">1. Reversible assembly of dodecahedron and cube with two types of modules that are basic to platonic solids. (Cube, Dodecahedron) 2. Reversible assembly of tetrahedron, octahedron and eicosahedron with a single module. (Tetrahedron, Octahedron and Eicosahedron)</cover>
	<cover vnum="05" inum="10">Complex loops formed during meiotic pairing of chromosomes as a result of overlapping inversions in <i>Drosophila nasuta nasuta</i>. Photograph courtesy: H A Ranganath, University of Mysore</cover>
	<cover vnum="05" inum="11">Mechanical analog computer to solve differential equations built under the guidance of Vannevar Bush.</cover>
	<cover vnum="05" inum="12">A computer generated drawing of the rotifer <i>Limnias melicerta</i>. (Picture Courtesy: T Ramakrishna Rao, Delhi University)</cover>
	<cover vnum="06" inum="01">Bamboos (Painting by Annapoorna Sitaram)</cover>
	<cover vnum="06" inum="02">Futuristic street signs and large area advertising display. A device made of polymer LED. (See article on Nobel Prize in Chemistry 2000)</cover>
	<cover vnum="06" inum="03">A peninsular element, the chameleon has recently invaded the desert. (For more details, read the article on pp. 76-85.)</cover>
	<cover vnum="06" inum="04">The picture shows a cloud of cold <sup>87</sup>Rb atoms held in a magneto-optic trap inside a vacuum chamber. The trap uses a combination of laser light and a spherical quadrupole magnetic field to cool the atoms to a temperature of less than one-thousandth of a degree above absolute zero, and simultaneously confine them to a small region of space. The laser light at 780 nm is constantly being absorbed and re-emitted by the trapped atoms. This resonance fluorescence is collected by a lens and captured on a CCD camera to `see' the cloud. In the picture shown, there are more than 10<sup>8</sup> atoms at a temperature of about 500 μK in a cloud of size 3 mm. Such atom traps are becoming increasingly important for experiments ranging from fundamental research in Bose-Einstein condensation and precision measurements to applications in atomic fountain clocks and nano-lithography. (The cover picture was taken by Umakant Rapol, Ajay Wasan and Vasant Natarajan, Department of Physics, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore.)</cover>
	<cover vnum="06" inum="05">Structure of benzene as proposed by Kekulé. (Courtesy: Suchit N Gopalpur)</cover>
	<cover vnum="06" inum="06">The Large Magellanic Cloud (ROE 14) (Reproduced from A Celebration of Colour in Astronomy by David Malin, <i>Current Science</i>, Vol. 60, No.1, 1991.)</cover>
	<cover vnum="06" inum="07">Rainbow parakeet (<i>Trichoglossus haematodus</i>). A colourful bird with long, narrow pointed tail. Found from East Indies and Australia to Vanatu. Has a distinct flight silhouette. (Photo Courtesy: S Sridhar, ARPS)</cover>
	<cover vnum="06" inum="08">The cover picture is a photomontage of the large equatorial sundial at the Jantar Mantar astronomical observatory situated in Jaipur. The stone observatory was built by Maharaja Sawai Jai Singh, a keen astronomer and mathematician, in the 18th century. The sundial is one of the biggest and most accurate sundials in the world with an accuracy of a few seconds. (See article, Standard Weights and Measures, page 44.) (Picture courtesy: Nikolaus von Bomhard) (http://www.bomhard.de/)</cover>
	<cover vnum="06" inum="09">Bonnet macaque (See classroom article Project Lifescape on The Macaques of India, page 94.) (Picture courtesy: Anindya Sinha)</cover>
	<cover vnum="06" inum="10">Collagen Assemblies From: http://www.rcsb.org/pdb/ molecules (See article on p.38)</cover>
	<cover vnum="06" inum="11">Forest Fire (See article on p.34)</cover>
	<cover vnum="06" inum="12">A collage on Indian Space Programme. Courtesy: ISRO</cover>
	<cover vnum="07" inum="01">Shoemaker-Levy 9 encounters Jupiter Courtesy: Jawaharlal Nehru Planetarium. Produced by M G Kulkarni (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="07" inum="02">The cover picture illustrates how chirality plays a very important role in the properties of molecules which interact with biological systems. (receptors, enzymes, etc.) (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="07" inum="03">Description of the flame by Faraday: It is steady and equal, and its general form is that which is represented in the diagram, varying with atmospheric disturbances, and also varying according to the size of the candle. It is bright, oblong, brighter at the top than towards the bottom, with the wick in the middle, and besides the wick in the middle, certain darker parts towards the bottom, where the ignition is not so perfect as in the part above. (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="07" inum="04">From the Bakshali Manuscript. This manuscript was unearthed in 1881 by a farmer in Bakhshali, a village about 80 kms to the north-east of Peshawar. It contains an exposition of basic arithmetic, extraction square-roots and cube-roots, arithmetic with fractions and practical problems of everyday commerce. It is written in a corrupt form of Sanskrit in Sarada script on Bhurjapatra (Birch-bark). A very good reference is <i>`The Bakhshali Manuscript'</i>, Takao Hayashi, Egbert Forsten, Groningen, 1995. (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="07" inum="05">Krishnarajsagar Dam at Mysore (Photo Courtesy: S Mohan, Asst. Photographer, Mysore Irrigation Projects) (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="07" inum="06">Origami model of a DNA double helix (Also see article on page 39) (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="07" inum="07">A male <i>C. sphinx</i> roosting in a tent under a palm leaf. (Also see article on page 65) (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="07" inum="08">Kavalur Observatory Photo by: D Rosario and N Kameswara Rao Courtesy: Indian Institute of Astrophysics (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="07" inum="09">Nitrogen Cycle Adapted from http://www.h2ou.com/h2images/ Nitrogen Cycle-lgr-F.jpg (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="07" inum="10">Male and female damselfly <i>Euphaea fraseri Photo: K A Subramanian (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</i></cover>
	<cover vnum="07" inum="11">A schematic drawing of the Large Electron Positron Collider ring, depicting the positions of the four detectors Aleph, Delphi, L3 and Opal, which took data for eleven years from 1989 to 2000. (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="07" inum="12">Crystal structure of diamond (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="08" inum="01">Hubble Space Telescope image of opaque dust clouds in IC2944 nebula. (Courtesy: ST ScI/NASA) (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="08" inum="02">Pictures of a new research airplane being developed. The first prototype flew only on 15th January 2003. (Courtesy: OCWT, Department of Aerospace, IISc) (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="08" inum="03">Insectivorous plants: <i>Sarracenia flava</i> and <i>Dionaea</i> (The images on the cover are used by permission of sarracenia.com)</cover>
	<cover vnum="08" inum="04">Schematic diagram shows the precession of Earth's axis and compares it with that of a top. (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="08" inum="05">The original experimental set-up of Hertz. (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="08" inum="06">1100°C-hot red lava dripping into a pit. Kilauea volcano, Hawaii. Photo by Hetu Sheth, July 2002. (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="08" inum="07">A colony of painted Storks. (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="08" inum="08">The First Observation of an Antiparticle In 1932 Carl Anderson observed an intriguing particle in the cloud chamber which he was using to study cosmic radiation. In the cloud chamber charged particles give rise to a trail of condensed droplets with which many properties of the particle can be determined. There were several interpretations possible. With the assumption that it was a well-known particle, it was either an electron moving downwards or a proton moving upwards. After careful investigations it was possible to exclude both possibilities. The electric charge was determined to be positive, that is opposite to the charge of the electron. This positive particle had a mass close to that of the electron. Carl Anderson had actually identified the first antiparticle, the positron as he called it, the antiparticle of the electron. In 1936 he received the Nobel Prize for his discovery of the positron. The positron moves upwards through a horizontal 3 mm lead plate and its trajectory is curved by a magnetic field. The direction was determined from the observation that the particle had lost energy going through the lead plate and was therefore curving more in the magnetic field. (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="08" inum="09">Superconductors are ideal diamagnetics and completely expel magnetic field at low temperatures. Normal things, like the frog in the cover picture, can do it as well if placed in a very strong magnetic field. Photo credits: High Field Magnet Laboratory, University of Nijmegen, The Netherlands (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="08" inum="10">Median egret (<i>Egretta intermedia</i>) about to take-off Photo Credit: Siddhartha Tambat, PhD student, CSA, IISc (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="08" inum="11">Mosaic texture of the B<sub>1</sub> liquid crystalline phase exhibited by compounds made of banana shaped molecules. (Photo courtesy: R Pratibha, RRI) (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="08" inum="12">Wright Brothers first flight (Credit: Courtesy of Special Collections and Archives, Wright State University) (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="09" inum="01">Kadupapa: A slender loris near Joga, Uttara Kannada (Credit: Kumara H N, University of Mysore) (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="09" inum="02">Rotation of a superfluid is not uniform buttakes place via a lattice of quantized vortices, whose cores (in blue) are parallel to the axis of rotation. Last year's Nobel Prize winners in physics contributed to the study of the quantum nature of superfluidity and superconductivity (see page 50). (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="09" inum="03">The famous X-ray diffraction photograph of B-DNA (photo 51) that Rosalind Franklin took while working at King's College, London. (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="09" inum="04">Ribbon model of AQPI (see article on p.61) (Picture courtesy: P Agre, Nobel Laureate, 2003). (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="09" inum="05">Heme portion of haemoglobin. (see article on p.51). (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="09" inum="06">Putt-Putt Boat (see articles on p.66 and 92) (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="09" inum="07">Deer antlers (see article on p.50) (Colour scheme for cover by Jayant Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="09" inum="08">Oilpainting by Werner Heisenberg, ca.1955. It shows the view from the terrace of his Urfeld-house. (Courtesy: Jochen H Heisenberg)</cover>
	<cover vnum="09" inum="09">The picture is that of Interview Island in the Andamans chain as seen by the LISS III sensor of IRS-1D on 26 January 2000. The island (133 sq km) is covered with dense and evergreen tropical forests, and is bordered with coral reefs, sea grasses and seaweed patches. The dense red colour depicts healthy vegetation of the forest that is sensitive to the infrared channel of the LISS sensor. Cyan and light blue rims of the island depict coral reefs at different depths. Amongst the Indian coral reefs, the Andaman corals are the last refuge but they too are under severe threat due to human exploitation. (Courtesy: National Remote Sensing Agency, Department of Space, India.)</cover>
	<cover vnum="09" inum="10">Two-dimensional vertical section through a turbulent plume. (Courtesy: G S Bhat, CAOS, IISc.)</cover>
	<cover vnum="09" inum="11">An artist's impression of DNA.</cover>
	<cover vnum="09" inum="12">The cover photograph is a composite of four images of the Sun, all taken by the SOHO spacecraft on September 2, 2003 within 15 minutes of each other. Each quadrant shows the Sun in a different monochromatic light. Clockwise: The red-orange image is in the light of singly ionized helium at 304 A; this is emitted from a region at 60,000 to 80,000 K. The yellow images is in the light of Fe XV (14-times ionized iron) at 284 A; this is emitted from a region at about 2.0-2.5 million K. The green image is at 195 A, emitted from a region at about 1.5 million K by Fe XII. The blue image at 171 A, is from a region at about 0.9-1.0 million K, emitted by Fe IX and Fe X.</cover>
	<cover vnum="10" inum="01">Pictures of Uranus taken during Voyager 2 mission. Sophisticated error correcting codes were used in the transmission of these images. (Credit: Public Information Office, Jet Propulsion 	Laboratory, California Institute of Technology, NASA, Pasadena, CA 91109, USA)</cover>
	<cover vnum="10" inum="02">The cover figure shows a simulation of the perturbation of sea level due to propagation of the tsunamis that were triggered by the earthquake of 26 December 2004, off the coast of Sumatra. It represents the conditions 5 hours after the earthquake. Pink implies sea level above mean sea level. See the article on p. 8 for more information. (Credit: Colour scheme for cover by Arun Mahale, NIO, Goa)</cover>
	<cover vnum="10" inum="03">Cover picture by Arun Kharat.</cover>
	<cover vnum="10" inum="04">A postage stamp showing the mushroom-like, spore-bearing fruiting bodies (basidiocarps) of <i>Armillaria mellea</i>.</cover>
	<cover vnum="10" inum="05">Explosion of the Arianae 5 satellite launching rocket in 1996. See article on p.26 for more details.</cover>
	<cover vnum="10" inum="06">Anna Bertha Roentgen's hand: the first X-ray photograph ever taken.</cover>
	<cover vnum="10" inum="07">Image of the Antarctic ozone hole, September 2000. See page 61 for more details. (Courtesy: NASA)</cover>
	<cover vnum="10" inum="08">Kármán vortex street visualized by injecting fluorocein dye and a sheet of green laser light. (Courtesy: Aerospace Engineering Department, IISc)</cover>
	<cover vnum="10" inum="09">The figure illustrates the giant tube worms that were discovered some years ago in the deep-sea in the vicinity of volcanic emissions. See article on page 23 (Drawing by S Mahadevan)</cover>
	<cover vnum="10" inum="10">CNO Cycle. See article on page 67. (Photo credit: Subhankar Biswas)</cover>
	<cover vnum="10" inum="11">A sparring match between male spotted deer (Photo: E Hanumantha Rao)</cover>
	<cover vnum="10" inum="12">World Year of Physics - 2005</cover>
	<cover vnum="11" inum="01">Human population movements out of Africa. See article on page 32.</cover>
	<cover vnum="11" inum="02">Propagating oxidation waves in unstirred layer of the ferroin-malonic acid BZ reaction. When the wave is broken at a certain point, a pair of spiral waves develop at this point. (See article on page 43) (Courtesy: Peter Ruoff). Source:www.ux.his.no/~ruoff/BZ_Phenomenology.html</cover>
	<cover vnum="11" inum="03">Borromean Link (see article on p.25)</cover>
	<cover vnum="11" inum="04">The illustration shows a dramatic consequence of the General Theory of Relativity, the bending of light by a gravitational field (`gravitational lensing'). See also p.7 and pp.45-55 for more details. (Photo Credit: Sunita Nair, RRI, Bangalore)</cover>
	<cover vnum="11" inum="05">Bromeliads - Pittendrigh's work on circadian rhythms started with his observation on the eclosion of mosquitoes from bromeliads. See article on page 22. (Photo Credit: Natasha Mhatre, CES, IISc)</cover>
	<cover vnum="11" inum="06">Space filling by regular polygons, soap froth and Picasso's painting. They all obey Euler's law (See page 55.)</cover>
	<cover vnum="11" inum="07">Female <i>Anopheles</i> after a blood-meal. (Taken from `Pictorial Identification Key for Indian Anophelines', National Institute of Malaria Research (NIMR), India; with permission)</cover>
	<cover vnum="11" inum="08">The spectacular dance of the peacock heralds the monsoon season. (Courtesy: Raghavendra Gadagkar, CES, IISc, Bangalore)</cover>
	<cover vnum="11" inum="09">An artist's representation of the extended space-time of loop quantum cosmology. (See article on pp.4-19.) (Courtesy: Dr Cliff Pickover, www.pickover.com)</cover>
	<cover vnum="11" inum="10">Models of some Archimedean solids (see article on p.8). Courtesy: P K Vyas, Vikram Sarabhai Community Science Centre, Ahmedabad.</cover>
	<cover vnum="11" inum="11">Cumulus clouds forming cloud streets over the western ghat; a close view of a growing cumulus congestus cloud. See article on p.8. (Courtesy: G S Bhat, CAOS, IISc)</cover>
	<cover vnum="11" inum="12">Title page of Newton's <i>Principia</i></cover>
	<cover vnum="12" inum="01">Dendritic architecture (See article on pp.60-66)</cover>
	<cover vnum="12" inum="02">The minute difference in the temperature of the microwave background radiation in different parts of the sky as measured by COBE. (See article on p.4) (Courtesy: NASA)</cover>
	<cover vnum="12" inum="03">Pictorial representation of the HOMO in N<sub>2</sub>. (See article on pp.70-76.)</cover>
	<cover vnum="12" inum="04">Image of Triton transmitted by Voyager 2. (Courtesy: NASA/JPL-Caltech) (See article on p.37)</cover>
	<cover vnum="12" inum="05">The Borromean triangles in the Marundheeswarar temple. (see article on p.41)</cover>
	<cover vnum="12" inum="06">Mangrove plants showing typical prop roots in Chorao Island, Goa</cover>
	<cover vnum="12" inum="07">LEMUR IIb - A four limbed robotic system designed to access the entire surface of the planetary body. (LEMUR: Limbed Excursion Mechanical Utility Robot) (Courtesy: NASA/JPL-Caltech)</cover>
	<cover vnum="12" inum="08">A rectangular shaped SmS sample under high pressure inside a DAC. See article on p.49. (Courtesy: A Jayaraman)</cover>
	<cover vnum="12" inum="09">Transformation of pneumococcal types. See article on p.83. (Reproduced from the <i>Journal of Experimental Medicine</i>, Vol.79, pp.137-158, 1944.)</cover>
	<cover vnum="12" inum="10">Picture of the HESS telescope for observations of high energy gamma rays, as depicted in a stamp issued by Namibia.</cover>
	<cover vnum="12" inum="11">Catalytic antibodies. See pp.6-21 for more details.</cover>
	<cover vnum="12" inum="12">The KC-135 aircraft used by NASA for generating low gravity conditions. See article on page 40. (Photo courtesy: NASA)</cover>
	<cover vnum="13" inum="01">Rosettes of maturing ascii in <i>Neurospora crassa</i>. See article on page 12.</cover>
	<cover vnum="13" inum="02">The upcoming satellite PLANCK to be launched in 2008 by the European Space Agency. It will make accurate maps of the cosmic microwave background radiation, which is known to be the best example of Planckian (black-body) radiation in Nature. Courtesy: European Space Agency</cover>
	<cover vnum="13" inum="03">An illustration of the flying frog Wallace discovered in the course of his travels to the Malayan peninsula. (From <i>The Malay Archipelago</i>)</cover>
	<cover vnum="13" inum="04">Artist’s impression of a black hole. (Courtesy:NASA)</cover>
	<cover vnum="13" inum="05">A view of the complex electronics of TIFRAC. (Courtesy: TIFR Archives)</cover>
	<cover vnum="13" inum="06">Spiral waves in CO oxidation on a Pt surface. (Courtesy: Gerhard Ertl)</cover>
	<cover vnum="13" inum="07">African bush elephant. (Credit: R Sukumar, IISc)</cover>
	<cover vnum="13" inum="08">Foucault Pendulum (Credit: IUCAA, Pune)</cover>
	<cover vnum="13" inum="09">An artist’s impression of <i>Pushpaka vimana</i>. (Credit: Subhankar Biswas)</cover>
	<cover vnum="13" inum="10">The head of the fruitfly Drosophila melanogaster. (Photo courtesy: Upendra Nongthomba, IISc)</cover>
	<cover vnum="13" inum="11">Cubic curves. See article on p.1027.</cover>
	<cover vnum="13" inum="12">Moon as viewed by Chandrayaan-1 terrain mapping camera on 4 November 2008. (Distance - 311200 km from moon) Courtesy: ISRO, Department of Space, Govt.of India</cover>
	<cover vnum="14" inum="01">Different modes of swimming. See article on pp.32-46. Redrawn from Review of Fish Swimming Modes for Aquatic Locomotion, <i>IEEE Journal of Oceanic Engineering</i>, Vol.24, No.2, pp. 237-252, 1999, D M Lane, M Sfakiotakis and J B C Davies, Heriot-Watt University.</cover>
	<cover vnum="14" inum="02">HMS Beagle in the waters of Tierra del Fuego, painted by Conrad Martens. (Credit: Wikimedia)</cover>
	<cover vnum="14" inum="03">Hubble Space Telescope, launched in 1991. Courtesy: NASA.</cover>
	<cover vnum="14" inum="04">Human chromosomes revealed by spectral karyotyping. (Credit: Dr Thomas Ried, NCI/NIH)</cover>
	<cover vnum="14" inum="05">A view of the J N Tata Statue from Indian Institute of Science Tower (Photo credit: K Sankara Rao, IISc; Courtesy: IISc Press)</cover>
	<cover vnum="14" inum="06">Watt’s double-acting steam engine.</cover>
	<cover vnum="14" inum="07">Surya Mandir, Konarak (see article on p.691).</cover>
	<cover vnum="14" inum="08">Harvesting light with molecules. (See article on p.782)</cover>
	<cover vnum="14" inum="09">A collage of Gustave Eiffel’s marvellous structures.</cover>
	<cover vnum="14" inum="10">Young to old inflorescences of a colour variant of the pernicious weed <i>Lantana camara</i>. Freshly opened flowers are yellow and change gradually to orange, scarlet and magenta. See p.1003.</cover>
	<cover vnum="14" inum="11">Sketches of solar prominences made by John Evershed along with the solar spectrum with which he discovered the Evershed effect. (Courtesy: IIA Archives)</cover>
	<cover vnum="14" inum="12">Frontispiece of Kepler’s <i>Rudolphine Tables</i>. (See article on p.1222)</cover>
	<cover vnum="15" inum="01">Collage of symbols of elements proposed by Dalton.</cover>
	<cover vnum="15" inum="02">Lattice points contained within the circle C (n) centered at the origin, and with radius <sqrt>n</sqrt> . See article on p.116.</cover>
	<cover vnum="15" inum="03">Transverse section of the ring porous wood (Red oak) Credit: The University of Wisconsin Plant Teaching Collection.</cover>
	<cover vnum="15" inum="04">Gharial, a critically endangered reptile with an estimated adult population of 200 in the wild. (Photo: Abhijit Das)</cover>
	<cover vnum="15" inum="05">Why do peacocks have long tails? (See article on p.434)</cover>
	<cover vnum="15" inum="06">The Pyramid of Giza (see article on p. 498)</cover>
	<cover vnum="15" inum="07">van der Waals molecules (see page 673).</cover>
	<cover vnum="15" inum="08">Photograph of laser-cooled cloud of ytterbium atoms taken with a CCD camera. The inventors of the CCD sensor shared the 2009 Nobel Prize in Physics. See page 732. (Courtesy: Atomic and Optical Physics Lab, IISc)</cover>
	<cover vnum="15" inum="09">Perkin’s Colour (Reproduced with permission: Society of Dyers and Colourists, UK)</cover>
	<cover vnum="15" inum="10">Image of a portion of the Orion molecular cloud. Such clouds were first theoretically considered by Sir Fred Hoyle. (Courtesy: NASA)</cover>
	<cover vnum="15" inum="11">Illustration of Purkinje cells by Cajal, 1899. (Courtesy: Instituto Santiago Ramón y Cajal, Madrid, Spain.)</cover>
	<cover vnum="15" inum="12">The title page of Gregor Reisch’s <i>Margarita Philosophica</i>. (See p.1065)</cover>
	<cover vnum="16" inum="01">Replica of Leeuwenhoek's microscope. (Courtesy: Wikimedia)</cover>
	<cover vnum="16" inum="02">Female spider (<i>Trochosa terricola, Lyco-sidae</i>) carrying spiderlings. (See article on p.180) Photo Credit: Jürgen Drissner, University Ulm, Botanical Garden.</cover>
	<cover vnum="16" inum="03">The cover shows linear relationship between energy and momentum of electronic excitations in graphene, very close to the Fermi energy. As a result the electronic excitations inside graphene behave as if they have no mass.</cover>
	<cover vnum="16" inum="04">Photograph showing a linear Paul trap used for trapping a chain of ions. The ions can be laser cooled to occupy a size that is smaller than the optical wavelength, called the Lamb-Dicke regime. Such tightly-confined ions have recoilless emission, which can be used for quantum computation or atomic clocks. (Courtesy: Atomic Physics Laboratory, IISc)</cover>
	<cover vnum="16" inum="05">This is the recent image of the microwave background and a `shadow' (in bright colours) cast by a nearby galaxy cluster, as predicted in 1969 by Zeldovich and his student Sunyaev (refer to the article on p.428). Image courtesy: European Space Agency.</cover>
	<cover vnum="16" inum="06">Ancient Indian Coins.</cover>
	<cover vnum="16" inum="07">`Garden' of biomolecular structures. Courtesy: Ms. G Sudha, Molecular Biophysics Unit, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore. See page 639 for details.</cover>
	<cover vnum="16" inum="08">An artistic `representation' of biological clocks. (Credit: Subhankar Biswas)</cover>
	<cover vnum="16" inum="09">`Hillside' by Richard Feynman.</cover>
	<cover vnum="16" inum="10">Numerical simulation of the gravitational radiation generated by the merger of two black holes by the NASA/Goddard Numerical Relativistic Astrophysics Group. Visualization: Chris Henze, NASA/Ames.</cover>
	<cover vnum="16" inum="11">Artistic representation of the substructure of atom. (Credit: Subhankar Biswas)</cover>
	<cover vnum="16" inum="12">Ancient Ajanta Cave painting using indigo dye. (Courtesy: wikipedia)</cover>
	<cover vnum="17" inum="01">Gasometer used by Lavoisier to precisely measure the masses of gases to show the conservation of mass in the synthesis of water from hydrogen and oxygen.(Reproduced with permission from Antoine-Laurent Lavoisier, <i>Elements of Chemistry</i>, Plate VIII, Dover Publication, Inc., 1965.)</cover>
	<cover vnum="17" inum="02">Wigner function for an even coherent state of radiation (see article on p.192).</cover>
	<cover vnum="17" inum="03"><i>Bakhshali</i> manuscript. (See article on pp.236-246.) (Courtesy: Bill Casselman)</cover>
	<cover vnum="17" inum="04">First prototype of the diesel engine. Courtesy: Wikipedia</cover>
	<cover vnum="17" inum="05">Schematic impression of hydrogen-induced Ostwald ripening. Top: Hydrogen atoms approaching the palladium nanocluster assembled film. Middle: The palladium atoms within the palladium cluster building blocks become free to move due to the interstitial hydrogen. Bottom: Some of the clusters become large at the expense of the smallest. See p.462. Courtesy: Marcel Di Vece, Utrecht University, The Netherlands.</cover>
	<cover vnum="17" inum="06">Microstructures of seashells. (see article on page 573).</cover>
	<cover vnum="17" inum="07">The cover photo shows images of a drop-let of size about 1 mm oscillating under AC electrowetting. (see article on p.682.) Courtesy: Physics of Complex Fluids, University of Twente, The Netherlands.</cover>
	<cover vnum="17" inum="08">A preferred <i>in vitro</i> cloning of plants is through multiple-shoot induction from axillary meristems and subsequent rooting of individual microshoots to obtain a complete plant. Figure shows stages in this process.</cover>
	<cover vnum="17" inum="09">Graeco-Latin Square. See p.820 for description.</cover>
	<cover vnum="17" inum="10">Pigment from Red Sandalwood. (See article on p.928.)</cover>
	<cover vnum="17" inum="11">The first Integrated Circuit chip. (See article on p.1035.)</cover>
	<cover vnum="17" inum="12">Evolution of the genetic code in Nature (See article on p.1136.)</cover>
	<cover vnum="18" inum="01">Collage of covers from some of Wheeler's textbooks</cover>
	<cover vnum="18" inum="02">Hydrilla verticillata, a keystone species.(See p.156)</cover>
	<cover vnum="18" inum="03">A candidate model for the atomic decoration of the decagonal quasi-unit cell forAl72Ni20Co8. (See p.271) Courtesy: P J Steinhardt</cover>
	<cover vnum="18" inum="04">A spectacular assembly of many crystals of Amethyst quartz from the Raman Research Institute museum. Pancharatnam used the Poincare sphere very effectively to understand the varied phenomena shown by them. (see article on page 309.) Courtesy: RRI, Bangalore </cover>
	<cover vnum="18" inum="05">Gemasolar Power Plant in Spain. Source: http://www.torresolenergy.com/TORRESOL/Press/torresol-energy-commissions-gemasolar-power-plant-in-spain. Reproduced with permission from Torresol Energy.</cover>
	<cover vnum="18" inum="06">Sequence of CCD images of the fluorescence from laser-cooled Ca+ ions trapped in a linear Paul tral. (See article on p.522) Courtesy : Guenter Werth's Group, University of Mainz, Germany.</cover>
	<cover vnum="18" inum="07">The buckyball contans 60 carbon atoms. Algorithms developed at the Visualization and Graphics Lab in IISc help identify symmetric structures in the buckyball at different resolutions directly from the electron density distribution around the buckyball molecule. (See article on p.615.)</cover>
	<cover vnum="18" inum="08"><i>Nelumbo nucifera</i> Gaertn., the sacred lotus (See article on p.732.) Photo Courtesy: Shrikant Ingalhalikar</cover>
	<cover vnum="18" inum="09">Circadian rhythms are endogenously generated close-to-24 h rhythms exhibited by organisms ranging from bacteria to humans and are governed by circadian clocks. Earth’s rotation about its axis results in cycling of environmental variables (light, temperature and humidity) that synchronize circadian clock to various behavioral and physiological phenomena. (See article on p.832) (Credit: Soham Saha, JNCASR)</cover>
	<cover vnum="18" inum="10">Sketch made by Niels Bohr in 1944 to illustrate the content of his debate with Einstein on the uncertainty principle at the 6th Solvay Conference in 1930.</cover>
	<cover vnum="18" inum="11">Modern fluorescence techniques allow the catalytic activity of single immobilized enzymes to be observed in real time. Adapted from Figure 2 of article on page 969.</cover>
	<cover vnum="18" inum="12">Spurious Correlation. (See p.1058.)</cover>
	<cover vnum="19" inum="01">It is a collage of a mechanical watch, a piano, and a nuclear explosion. All three are related to one of Fermi's legendary skills. He was reputed for making rapid and insightful estimates of physical quantities in many real life situations. For more details see the article on p.73.</cover>
	<cover vnum="19" inum="02">Norman Borlaug, father of "Green Revolution" saved the world from hunger by cultivating high yeidling rice and wheat varieties (Credit: Ayan Guha)</cover>
	<cover vnum="19" inum="03">IBM's Watson in the quiz show Jeopardy! (see article on p.222)</cover>
	<cover vnum="19" inum="04">Tiling of the plane by 17 wallpaper groups. See page 304.</cover>
	<cover vnum="19" inum="05">Intracellular protein trafficking between the organelles and their biogenesis, and degradation pathways in a eukaryotic cell. see p.443.</cover>
	<cover vnum="19" inum="06">ORTEP diagrams of alizarin and indigo. Alizarin crystallizes in two polymorphic forms, both mono-clinic. They are twinned and disordered, which is why X-ray structure looks as though it has more than two hydroxy groups</cover>
	<cover vnum="19" inum="07">Left: Polarizing microscope images of (top) naural and (bottom) totally synthetic crystals of vitamin B12 (R B Woodward). Right: Structure of vitamin B12. (See article on p.624.)</cover>
	<cover vnum="19" inum="08">Molecular simulation of an ice crystal. This view is looking down the hexagonal channel in the crystal. See article on page 671. Courtesy: Shekhar Garde, Linda Schadler and Richard W Siegel, http://www.molecularium.com</cover>
	<cover vnum="19" inum="09">Two themes with a strong geometric content, relating to the work of Vladimir Arnold. The upper figure shows his famous 'cat map' which illustrates how a simple, reversible transformation of the plane applied to a rather orderly figure (a cat) can apparently create a fully mixed figure. The lower panel shows how a simple rule of optics can generate singularities; the high brightness along the cusp in the ray diagram, and the corresponding sharp folding over of the wavefront into three sheets. The astronomical backdrop evokes the fundamental contribution of the KAM theory to the dynamics of celestial bodies. (See articles on pages 787 and 797.) Credit: http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Arnold_cat.png</cover>
	<cover vnum="19" inum="10">Leather products. See article on p.961</cover>
	<cover vnum="19" inum="11">The Mandelbrot set is named after Benoit Mandelbrot (20th November 1924-14th October 2010) was a Polish-born, French and American mathematician. This is the set of complex numbers c for which the sequence of points defined by the iteration 'square and add c to get the next point' starting from 0, remains in a bounded region. This is a fractal, meaning a pattern composed of smaller copies of iteself and infinitum. (See article on page 1000.)</cover>
	<cover vnum="19" inum="12">Stamp issued by the Department of Posts, India to commemorate International Year of Crystallography 2014 (IYCr).</cover>
	<cover vnum="20" inum="01">Travancore tortoise, Anamalai Tiger Reserve (See article on page 47.)</cover>
	<cover vnum="20" inum="02">Buckminster Fuller's Designs (See article on page 98.)</cover>
</res>
